All right, today's דף, daf, we are going to see if we
can complete דף למד, daf Lamed, but we pick up on the
middle of כ"ט עמוד ב', Chaf Tet Amud Bet, and we are
up to the following:
לימא כתנאי. Lema k'tannai. It is top of כ"ט עמוד ב', Chaf
Tet Amud Bet, six lines down, line starts with the word כתנאי.
k'tannai. So this debate of יוחנן Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
about whether the נזיר Nazir that a father can make his son
a נזיר Nazir is a special הלכה Halacha by נזירות Neziros that
a father has this ability to impose it on his son, or
whether it's all Rabbinic and it's some type of a form of
חינוך, Chinuch, and in the process of this חינוך, Chinuch, it allows
us to skirt or to compromise a lot of other principles, so
it's quite fascinating. So the גמרא Gemara says, let's say this is
tied, this is paralleled a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, or it is
a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. And here's the ברייתא. Baraita. עד מתי
מדיר בנו בנזיר, Ad matai madzir beno benazir, to what age can
a father make his son a נזיר? Nazir? עד שיביא שתי שערות,
Ad sheyavi shtei se'arot, דברי רבי, Divrei Rabbi, until he brings two
pubic hairs, until he's a בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, meaning plus the
age of 13, that's implicit. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר עד שיגיע
לעונת נדרים, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda omer ad sheyagia le'onat nedarim, until
he comes to the stage of making vows. Something that we have
not really fully explored yet is is that a child, boy or
girl, a year before their age of majority, a year before a
girl's בת מצוה Bat Mitzvah and a year before a boy's בר
מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, can make a vow and it's binding if the
person understands what the sort of, you know, the meaning of the
vow. You know, that it's the making of a vow to God
and they have basic understanding of what they're doing, that's considered a
מופלא סמוך לאיש. mufla samuch l'ish. The מופלא mufla from the word
להפליא lehafli to enunciate the power create a vow before a person
is actually an adult. So it's a very fascinating area of הלכה,
Halacha, and again there's a question there, is it דאורייתא, D'Oraita, דרבנן,
D'Rabbanan, we're about to sort of see some of that in a
minute. So one person says, if you are doing the vow for
your son, you can only do it until the age that your
son is of the age of making vows himself, which is this
year of this year of עונת נדרים. onat nedarim. So the גמרא
Gemara says, well let's take a look. מאי לאו תנאי היא, Mai
lav tannai hi, isn't this debate of תנאים Tannaim our debate? דדברי
רבי סבר הלכה בנו בנזיר, DeDivrei Rabbi savar Halacha beno benazir, רבי
Rabbi holds that it's the ability for power to do a for
a father to do it on his son is a הלכה, Halacha,
it's like a הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, it's this you
know biblical power that he has. We don't have a basis for
it in the verses, but this is just a special
power that
a father has for his son as long as the son is
a minor, as long as the son is sort of under the
auspices of the father, עד שיביא שתי שערות, ad sheyavi shtei se'arot,
until he becomes an adult. So even though the son is maybe
to some degree an adult in terms of he can make his
own vows, but this is about the father's power as it were
over the son and the son is still considered a minor. ורבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה דאמר עד שיגיע לעונת נדרים, VeRabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda
de'amar ad sheyagia le'onat nedarim, and according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda that says that the principle is, and here
it's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, yesterday we quoted
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it was a question whether we're referring to
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda or רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina, anyway in this ברייתא Baraita it's רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda who says that it's until
he's the age of 12, סבר כדי לחנכו במצוות. savar k'dei l'chancho
bemitzvos. His approach would be would be consistent with the idea that
the power of the father to do this is a form of
חינוך, Chinuch, וכיון דנפיק מרשותיה, ve'kivan de'nafik me'reshusei, once the son is
outside of the father's control, תו לא מחייב, tu lo mechayev, he's
no longer obligated. Now again, it's not exactly clear what does it
mean out of the father's control? I mean he's still he's still
a minor, light in all other areas or whatever in general he's
not let's say obligated for his transgressions, maybe and isn't you know
but nevertheless it's understanding that the idea of חינוך Chinuch in an
area relating to vows and נזיר Nazir is less relevant when the
child is empowered to do it himself. חינוך Chinuch is the idea
that the father is going to train the child and the child
means that the child is not yet sort of you know an
agent in that area himself. Once the child can sort of do
it himself, so look you know there's plenty of things that even
once you're an adult you know you could help to have a
little people a little advice a little training a little guidance in
a lot of areas of life, okay but nevertheless
the point
is
is that if it's about חינוך Chinuch and in this particular area
the kid is no longer a minor in this area then חינוך
Chinuch is no longer relevant, okay or is no that would not
be something that the father would be empowered. Okay but again it's
not a clear lineup because you could you know you could be
because because again it's not black and white that it would divide
along those lines which is what the גמרא's Gemara going to. I
mean, no, that's not necessarily the line, the division. I could go
either way here. דכולי עלמא הלכה היא בנדר. dechulei alma Halacha hi
benader. First of all, I could say that everybody says it's a
הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai. והכא במופלא סמוך לאיש קמיפלגי. vehacha
bemufla samuch le'ish kamiflagi. The debate is what status you give this
idea of somebody who is a מופלא mufla who can enunciate vows,
who's legally able to create vows but is not yet an adult.
רבי סבר מופלא סמוך לאיש דרבנן. Rebbi savar mufla samuch le'ish derabanan.
Rebbi holds that that whole category is a rabbinic category. Again, similar
to the question of can a father make his son a נזיר
nazir is also a similar question about when a person makes vows,
an age before adulthood, is that binding biblically or not, or is
only rabbinic? Right, all these areas where you know the גמרא Gemara
could ask similar questions. I don't understand, how could that be binding
rabbinic? Would you give the guy lashes if he was 12 years
old or a girl 11 and made a vow and then violated
it? You know, similar types of questions where we're going to act
as if it's biblical but the whole thing might really be rabbinic.
So the same way we're sort of saying that by the father
making his son a נזיר, nazir, there's similar questions about this idea
about making vows a year before adulthood. So Rebbi could be of
the opinion that that whole category is rabbinic. ואתא דאורייתא דחי דרבנן.
ve'ata de'oraisa dachi derabanan. And therefore
the biblical way that the father is empowered to impose נזירות neziros
on the son, assuming it's a הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe Misinai,
obviously overrides any rabbinic independence that the son might have in the
area of vows. That's only some rabbinic status. So that would be
the opinion that the father could do it because the whole independence
that the son has at the age of 12 is only
rabbinic. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה סבר מופלא סמוך לאיש דאורייתא. Rebbi Yose
b'Rebbi Yehuda savar mufla samuch le'ish de'oraisa. No, it's biblical. And therefore
even if it's not based on חינוך, chinuch, even if it's based
on הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe Misinai, nevertheless if the son is
an independent agent in the matter of vows, then even then the
father is, then since a נזירות neziros is a vow, even if
it's not based on חינוך, chinuch, the father shouldn't be able to
impose it on the son. Okay? So as opposed to before that
somehow we thought if it was a הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe
Misinai, then it wouldn't matter that the son is independent in this
area because big picture the son is still a minor. Here the
גמרא Gemara is saying no, even if it's not based on חינוך,
chinuch, why should the father be able to impose this on the
son if in this area, the area of נדרים, nedarim, the son
is, the son is independent? So the father he should be out
of the father's רשות reshus even not through a חינוך chinuch lens,
but just in a sense of a power like lens. If the
son is empowered, the father should not be empowered. But that would
only be if the idea of מופלא סמוך לאיש mufla samuch le'ish
is דאורייתא. de'oraisa. If the son has this independence at a biblical
level. If he only has it at a rabbinic level, then the
father can still go ahead and impose נזירות neziros on the son.
Yeah. Is הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai always considered logically to
be דאורייתא de'oraisa level? Yes. I mean look, הלכה, Halacha, okay, תפילין
Tefillin for
example and stuff like that. Yes, yes, yes.
So
this גמרא Gemara clearly assumes that הלכה Halacha means דאורייתא. de'oraisa. But
there are two questions on that which I should sort of mention.
One is that there are times הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai
is used more rhetorically, metaphorically, not literally, and right exactly and does
not really mean דאורייתא, de'oraisa,
but really means like it's like a you know I mean anyway
there's a classic example that there's a משנה Mishnah says הלכה עמון
ומואב מעשרין מעשר עני בשביעית, Halacha Amon uMoav measrin maaser ani beshvi'is,
a משנה Mishnah
in עדיות, Eduyos, where basically it's talking about a rabbinic obligation of
the lands outside of Israel to take תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'maasros. It's
clearly rabbinic and it uses the phrase הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe
Misinai. So there are times when it's not used literally. Actually Christine
Hayes has a scholar in Yale has a I think Yale, right?
Yeah, yeah. Anyway she's got a whole good article on the development
of the concept of הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe Misinai, so that
when it you know might you know and what it might have
meant at different stages in terms
of of the Tannaitic and Amoraic period. That's point number one. Point
number two is the גמרא Gemara never said הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha
Lemoshe Misinai. I was waiting for somebody to call me on this.
The גמרא Gemara just said הלכה. Halacha. Now there's a general assumption
that the word הלכה Halacha means הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe Misinai,
but there are actually some question about that that whether הלכה Halacha
might actually mean I think there's a נצי"ב Netziv that says that
הלכה Halacha in רש"י Rashi what, whatever he he I'm not remembering
the specifics but he basically says הלכה Halacha might just mean it's
an ancient tradition that it doesn't have the same meaning as הלכה
למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai. The point though here is that the
גמרא Gemara is clearly assuming that the position of הלכה Halacha means
דאורייתא. de'oraisa. You know that's clearly coming up in this dynamic. If
it's a הלכה, Halacha, then it would override a דרבנן derabanan status
that the son has but you know but it wouldn't override a
דאורייתא de'oraisa status that the son has. So here it's clearly assuming
that הלכה Halacha means that. Now the difference here might be that
often הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai is some independent law. Like
you know here it's telling you a parameter within the דאורייתא de'oraisa
laws of נזירות. neziros. So as opposed if you just said some
new thing is a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai or הלכה,
Halacha, maybe you don't mean it goes back to משה, Moshe, maybe
you don't mean it's דאורייתא. de'oraisa. But here what we're saying is
this is something that we always knew was part of the parameters
of נזירות, neziros, so ultimately it is... folded into a דאורייתא d'Oraisa
דין. din. Correct. So it might be different here because you're dealing
with something that's already a דאורייתא d'Oraisa category. Exactly. Exactly. You're giving
a detail in a דאורייתא d'Oraisa law. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Anyway, so if could be that
everybody agrees that the idea that a father makes the son a
נזיר nazir is not based on a rabbinic concept of חינוך, chinuch,
it's part of the laws of נזירות. nezirus. Would it override a
son who is 12 and can make his own vows? Well, if
that's a status of independence that the תורה Torah recognizes, then the
father would lose control in that case. If it's only a rabbinic
status of independence, then the father would still have control in that
case. So that's version number one.
What if it's from the דאורייתא d'Oraisa and the son has certain
independence counts on his own, would the father have the opportunity to
be מתיר matir the נדר neder of the son?
No, there's no... oh, you mean because of קרובים? krovim? I mean...
yeah, I mean a קרוב karov can be on... can be מתיר
matir a נדר. neder. You mean מתיר matir or you mean to
be a מפר? meifer? There's no הפרה. hafara.
No, there's no הפרה. hafara. הפרה hafara is only husband and wife.
Or no, father and daughter, not father and son. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's one approach. Okay. רבי
Rebbi says that it's דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'is eima, another
approach: דכולי עלמא כדי לחנכו במצות. d'chulei alma k'dei l'chancho b'mitzvos. Everyone
agrees it's from a חינוך chinuch perspective and it's all דרבנן. d'rabanan.
ומופלא סמוך לאיש דרבנן. u'mufla samuch l'ish d'rabanan. And the idea of
מופלא mufla is דרבנן. d'rabanan. Because if it was biblical, then the...
if the son had independence, if it was דאורייתא d'Oraisa speaking independent,
it would be bizarre that the father could impose חינוך chinuch over
the son when his status was fully independent even from the תורה's
Torah perspective. But here what you have is two דרבננ'ס d'rabanans running
up against one another. That the חינוך chinuch is a rabbinic responsibility
of the father and the son has rabbinic independen... is independent rabbinically
as well. So how is those going to... so which one is
going to win out?
Okay. ומופלא סמוך לאיש דרבנן. u'mufla samuch l'ish d'rabanan. רבי סבר אתי
חינוך דרבנן ודחי מופלא סמוך לאיש דרבנן וסימן. Rebbi savar asi chinuch
d'rabanan v'dachi mufla samuch l'ish d'rabanan v'siman. So now though, we will
give more weight to the father's role of חינוך. chinuch. We'll say
the son's independence is only דרבנן, d'rabanan, the father's obligation of חינוך
chinuch is דרבנן. d'rabanan. In this case we're going to tip in
favor of the father's role as חינוך chinuch and we're going to
let the father still continue to make the son a נזיר. nazir.
And we're also obviously, I mean we're already compromising so many other
laws in terms of חולין בעזרה chullin b'azarah and you know, and
שחיטה לעוף, shechitah l'of, so we'll also override the son's independence. רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה דאמר עד שיביא שתי שערות Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda
d'amar ad she'yavi shtei se'aros says no, once the son is fit
to make
vows because קסבר לא אתי חינוך דרבנן ודחי מופלא סמוך לאיש. kasavar
lo asi chinuch d'rabanan v'dachi mufla samuch l'ish. No, once the rabbis
made the son recognize the son's independence in the role of נדרים
nedarim even at the age of 12, so that also took him
out of the category of חינוך. chinuch. Okay, so you cannot link
it into this question about the age whether it goes by 13
or whether it goes by 12 because that would... that could still
depend, that could work either way based on whether the question of
what's biblical and what's rabbinic. And even if it is based... if
it's based on חינוך chinuch certainly once the son has independence, חינוך
chinuch might be... the father might not have a role of חינוך.
chinuch. But who knows? Maybe the rabbis sort of did away with
the son's independence to allow חינוך chinuch in this area. Or even
if it's a הלכה, halacha,
and even if it's
דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, the son's independence is a biblical idea as well at
that age of 12, then the father's power would not extend in
that case even if it weren't based on חינוך. chinuch.
Yes. Something interesting about the particular area of נזירות. nezirus. He knows...
knows who he's doing it for and the rabbis empower him in
this kind of a case and that would apply, but let's say
he's younger and doesn't really know what he's doing.
No, it wouldn't matter. But we'll get to אונס נדרים. ones nedarim.
But no, you need both criteria. Same way you need 13 and
two pubic hairs, you need 12 and to know what you're doing.
It's the combination of years and knowledge, yes.
סמוך לאיש סמוך לפרקו. Samuch l'ish samuch l'pirko.
In other words, yeah, סמוך, samuch, close to being an adult, correct.
Okay. נימא הני תנאי כי הני תנאי. Neima hani tannai ki hani
tannai. Okay,
how about the following תנאים? tannaim? If we just quoted two תנאים
tannaim that debate whether it's 13 or 12, let's say it's linked
to the following תנאים tannaim that also debate if it's 13 or
12. And there's actually a funny statement because it's not just "these
are like these", actually the same תנאים. tannaim. It's רבי Rebbi and
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda. So it's a strange
intro, but okay. דתניא, Detanya, we taught a ברייתא. braisa. מעשה ברבי
חנינא. Ma'aseh b'Rebbi Chanina. There was a story with רבי חנינא. Rebbi
Chanina. שהדירו אביו בנזיר. She'hadiro aviv b'nazir. His father made him a
נזיר. nazir.
You see the גמרא's Gemara not making the... the משנה's Mishnah not
making this stuff up. This stuff happened. והביאו לפני רבן גמליאל. V'hevi'o
lifnei Rabban Gamliel. And they brought him in front of רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel to figure out like what's he going to do now.
The נזירות nezirus is over, bring a קרבן. korban. והיה רבן גמליאל
בודק בו לידע אם הביא שתי שערות אם לאו הביא. V'haya Rabban
Gamliel bodek bo leida im hevi shtei se'aros im lav hevi. And
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was trying to figure out did he... did
he bring two pubic hairs or not? Was he an adult? So
when his father made him a נזיר, nazir, was his father able
to make him a נזיר? nazir? Maybe the kid was an adult
at that time and the father's act of נזירות nezirus would not
work. So אם לאו הביא. im lav hevi. So that's the first
position. רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbi Yose omer, but רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose
says no, no, no. The question wasn't whether the father did it
when the kid was... whether the kid was bar mitzvahed or not.
The question was לידע אם הגיע לעונת נדרים אם לאו. leida im
higia l'onas nedarim im lav. He wanted to know if the kid
had gotten to... The age of making vows a year before בר
מצוה, bar mitzvah, which means to check, presumably the age of the
kid was known. So in one version, the kid was thirteen and
the question was: Did he have two pubic hairs? That would determine
if he was an adult. The other case, the kid was twelve
and the question was: Did he know how he was to for
what sake he was making vows or not? So that would be
the other requirement outside in addition to age that is required for
this status of עונת נדרים. onas nedarim. So that's the debate. Did
the father have the power to do it? So רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel was trying to figure that out and the question was: Either
was the kid 13 with two pubic hairs or was the kid
12 and knowing and knows how to make vows. And if that
was true, the father did not have the power to do it.
Okay. So okay אם לאו. im lav. אמר לו. amar lo. So
רבי חנינא Rebbi Chanina said to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, his I
guess his name at that stage was just חנינא. Chanina. Okay, so
said to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, אמר לו. amar lo. רבי, Rebbi,
אל תצטער לבדוק קני. al tista'er livdok kani. You know what? You
don't have to bother checking me. אם קטן אני אהא בשביל אבא.
im katan ani eyei bishvil abba. Look, if I was a minor
when my father did impose נזירות nezirus on me, I'm a נזיר
nazir because of what my father did. אם גדול אני, im gadol
ani, and if I'm an adult, אהא בשביל עצמי. eyei bishvil atzmi.
I accept נזירות nezirus on myself now anyway. So look, I'll save
you the trouble. Either way I'll be a נזיר. nazir.
So the question was a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham.
Yeah, so I think he was הגיע לעונת נדרים. higia le-onas nedarim.
Okay. אמר רבן גמליאל ונשקו על ראשו. amar Rabban Gamliel venashko al
rosho. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel stood up and kissed him on his
head. אמר לו, amar lo, אמרנו, amarnu, he said, מובטח אני בזה
שמורה הלכה בישראל. muvtach ani be-zeh she-moreh halacha be-Yisrael. Oh, such a
תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. I know that this young man will eventually
be a teacher of הלכה halacha in Israel. אמרו לו, amru lo,
היו ימים מועטים, hayu yamim mu'atim, it was not long time, עד
שהורה הלכה בישראל, ad she-horah halacha be-Yisrael, until it actually came true
and he grew up to be a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
and a rabbi and he taught הלכה halacha in Israel. Now, so
here we have this question again, the same question about whether it
is thirteen or twelve. Now the גמרא Gemara has a question. בשלמא
לרבי יוסי בר יהודה או לרבי יוסי, bishlama le-Rebbi Yosei bar Yehuda
o le-Rebbi Yosei, again this whole question of which רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yosei is this, דאמר עד שיגיע לעונת נדרים, de-amar ad she-yagia le-onas
nedarim, היינו דקאמר אם קטן אני אהא בשביל אבא. hayinu de-ka'amar im
katan ani eyei bishvil abba. So we get it. He's saying, Look,
if I'm a minor then it'll be my father and if not
I'll do it myself because I'm הגיע לעונת נדרים. higia le-onas nedarim.
This question is not going to be a real question. The רא"ש
Rosh says we're just sort of getting asking this throwaway question to
get to the next question. But anyway, here's the question. אלא רבי
דאמר עד שיביא שתי שערות, ela Rebbi de-amar ad she-yavi shetei se'aros,
according to רבי Rebbi that says that it's until he is an
adult and brings two pubic hairs, ואם גדול אני אהא בשביל עצמי,
ve-im gadol ani eyei bishvil atzmi, and he's saying if I'm an
adult I'll be for
myself, הא ברשותא דאבוה קאים, ha birshuso de-avua kayam, he's still in
his father's control. Now what the heck do you mean? He says,
if I'm an adult means if I am thirteen and have two
pubic hairs then I'm an adult. So the גמרא, Gemara, so the
רא"ש Rosh says, the גמרא Gemara for somehow bizarrely thinks that even
though רבי Rebbi says that the test was to see if he
was an adult and had two pubic hairs, when the kid, חנינא,
Chanina, said if I'm an adult, it meant if I, if I've
gotten to עונת נדרים. onas nedarim. So the גמרא Gemara is saying,
well why is it enough that he got to עונת נדרים onas
nedarim if according to רבי Rebbi he needs to actually be a
full adult? But the I mean it's a silly question because the
answer is no, what he meant was if I'm an adult. So
according to רבי Rebbi who says it's about being 13 and two
pubic hairs, that's what he was saying. He wasn't saying עונת נדרים.
onas nedarim. So the גמרא Gemara says fine. אלא דאמר אהא בשביל
אבא אהא בשביל עצמי, ela de-amar eyei bishvil abba eyei bishvil atzmi,
okay fine. But what are you saying is, I get it's like
it's hard to know what the question is, it's hard to see
the answer. But the basic point was no, no, even according to
רבי Rebbi he means either if I am, it doesn't mean if,
if according to רבי Rebbi that the test was to see if
he was an adult or not, if he had two pubic hairs,
so that's what the kid was saying. If I'm not an adult,
then I'm for my father and if I'm an adult and I'm
13 with two pubic hairs I'll be for myself. Fine, that was
like a throwaway question. Here's really our question. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
אי אייתי שתי שערות מעיקרא, i aysei shetei se'aros me-ikara, look, says
the גמרא Gemara fine, let's take a look from the perspective of
the 13. Whether it's the 12 or the 13 it doesn't matter,
but here's our question. If he had two pubic hairs from before
when the father made him a נזיר, nazir, קאים בנזירות דיליה. ka'im
binezirus diley. I'm sorry, fine yes, when the father made him a
נזיר, nazir, and then קאים בנזירות דיליה, ka'im binezirus diley, then the
fact that he basically, the father made him a נזיר, nazir, he
was already an adult, but he maybe silently acquiesced, maybe he even
verbally said yes or something of that nature, then fine, then he's
his own נזיר, nazir, that we understand.
ובסוף uvelasof if he had only the two hairs at the end,
he went, he was a minor when the father did it, he
spent the 30 days, after the 30 days was over, then the
kid became an adult, that also we understand the case. קאים בנזירות
דאבוה, ka'im binezirus de-avua, then it would be the father. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says look, when did he become an adult? There
are three possible scenarios. He was already an adult when the father
did it, he was an adult after the end of the נזירות,
nezirus, or he became an adult in the middle. So the גמרא
Gemara says we're going to have to figure out that last case.
The first two cases are easy. If he was an adult when
the father did it, then it was his own, somehow his silent
acquiescence, or maybe he verbally said yes, he fine, we can understand
he's his own נזיר nazir and it's done after 30 days. If
he became an adult after the 30 days was over, it's also
done at the end of the 30 days, that's what the father
did. But what happens if If he became an adult in the
middle, right? And we're going to assume, and this is by the
way not explicit in the גמרא Gemara but it's explicit in the
תוספתא, Tosefta, that if the father makes his son a נזיר, nazir,
and in the middle of the 30 days, the son becomes an
adult, that's sort of like the case in the משנה Mishna where
the son or the relatives protest. Remember the case of the son
or the relatives protesting or shaving? Once he reached an age where
he now is independent, that terminates the father's נזירות nezirot even if
he doesn't do anything, just by virtue of becoming an adult. So
if that's true and the גמרא Gemara is sort of assuming that,
we have how could רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina or let's say חנינא
Chanina say, hey, don't worry, either way I'm a נזיר. nazir. It's
not true either way you're a נזיר. nazir. You're a נזיר nazir
if you only became an adult at the end of 30 days
or if you
were already an adult at the beginning. But if you became an
adult sometime in the middle, right, let's say רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
was checking him on day ten, right? So if he only became
an adult then on day ten, so he would need 30 days
from that point onwards, because becoming an adult in the middle would
have interrupted the period that had preceded, right?
So yes, but or ended,
right, ended, meaning yeah, you have
to do 30 days once you wanted to accept it upon yourself.
Right. Right. And if what חנינא Chanina was saying was, I accept
it upon myself regardless, right, fine, you accept it upon yourself, but
then it needs to be 30 days from this point, not you
can't just say either way 30 days from the outset.
Yeah. You're trying to get to the question of when did he
become a גדול? gadol? But if you're talking about it wasn't on
the same day that the father made him a נזיר, nazir, then
he didn't accept a נזירות nezirot when he became a גדול. gadol.
Right. He didn't accept a נזירות nezirot when he became a גדול.
gadol.
Exactly. Exactly. So maybe he hasn't even been a נזיר nazir all
together, exactly.
And the נזירות nezirot doesn't really end, it just dissipates or disappears.
He doesn't have to bring a קרבן.
korban. Right, it doesn't end naturally, it's sort of like when the
husband annuls his wife's vows or like or like the case of
מיכה Micha in the משנה, Mishna, correct. So that's the גמרא's Gemara's
question. ואי איכא במציעא מאי, Ve'i ika bemetzia mai, but if it
comes in the middle, what would be the story then? הניחא לרבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, Haniicha leRabbi Yossi beRabbi Yehuda, now somehow the גמרא's
Gemara's going to think this is easier if we're thinking about עונת
נדרים, onat nedarim, דאמר עד שיגיע לעונת נדרים. de'amar ad sheyagia le'onat
nedarim. אלא לרבי דאמר עד שיביא שתי שערות מאי איכא למימר. Ella
leRabbi de'amar ad sheyavi shtei se'arot mai ika lemeimar.
So what, now why is it easier if it's an issue about
עונת נדרים? onat nedarim? So the גמרא Gemara seems to assume, because
remember that תוספתא Tosefta I mentioned said when the kid becomes an
adult, it interrupts it in the middle, okay, that or interrupts it
or ends it in the middle, that that would only be the
case of שתי שערות. shtei se'arot. That if, because that's really a
biblical status of being an adult and that really breaks the נזירות
nezirot beforehand. But if it's the issue about עונת נדרים, onat nedarim,
so there we can say, look, since the father was entitled to
impose it at the beginning, right, whether that's based on חינוך chinuch
or whether that's based on, well actually the גמרא Gemara assumes that
if it's עונת נדרים onat nedarim it's within the rule of חינוך
chinuch or whatever. Anyway, if the father's entitled, well no maybe not
forget that. And if the father's whatever empowered either for חינוך chinuch
or just because that's the הלכה halacha to impose it, then the
fact that the kid has asserted a certain amount of independence in
the area of נדרים nedarim is not strong enough to change his
status. That's only a limited ability to make vows for himself. So
if he already started as a נזיר nazir because the father was
able to impose it at the beginning of the process, עונת נדרים
onat nedarim would not interrupt that, would not end that. Okay. What
would end it is that you've completely changed your legal status. If
you've gone from being a minor to being an adult, then even
if you were in the middle of some process that your father
had begun, you're now completely new legal status and it would end.
Okay. So the גמרא's Gemara's name that, so that's the גמרא's Gemara's
question. We got a question if the idea is being a being
a בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, being an adult. That should completely end
the נזירות nezirot that a father imposed earlier. If it's עונת נדרים,
onat nedarim, it's very nice that now you're able to do certain,
you know, now you're able to make your own vows, but you're
in the middle of a vow that your father imposed on you,
that doesn't end. Your basic legal status is the same. Okay. If
you had that independence at the beginning, your father couldn't have imposed
the vow. But now that your father did impose the vow, that
process isn't going to end just because you can do it yourself.
Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara's assumption. הניחא לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
דאמר עד שיגיע לעונת נדרים. Haniicha leRabbi Yossi beRabbi Yehuda de'amar ad
sheyagia le'onat nedarim. According to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yossi beRabbi
Yehuda that it's about an age of making vows, the fact that
you got to that age that now you can make your own
vows doesn't stop a נזירות nezirot that your father imposed. אלא לרבי
דאמר עד שיביא שתי שערות מאי איכא למימר. Ella leRabbi de'amar ad
sheyavi shtei se'arot mai ika lemeimar. But רבי Rabbi who says that
it's about being an adult,
when you become an adult, your previous status should totally end from
what your father did, you're completely now a new legal status, you
shouldn't be held by that. So so that whole נזירות nezirot ends.
Your argument is exactly the opposite.
I understand, but let's work with the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says, המה אמרי לרבי מאי איכא קנתה עד
דיתיב דיליה ויתיב דאבוה. Hama amri leRabbi mai ika kanta ad d'yativ
diley ve'yativ d'avuhu. You're right, according to רבי Rabbi you would not
necessarily be able to say it doesn't matter ממה נפשך, mimah nafshach,
it's 30 days from the outset. It's not necessarily 30 days from
the outset. If he became an adult in the middle, then it
would not be from the outset. So for רבי Rabbi it would
have to be both the father's 30 days from the outset and
30 days from the time he became an adult. So therefore if
you wanted to play it safe and I don't know when I
became an adult, but I'm saying to you right now that if
I'm an adult right now, well actually it wouldn't
work because he could say if... the end of 30 days, the
end of 30 days, and then say, if I was a,
let's see, if I'm not an adult now, then I'm not doing
anything, right, and I finished the נזירות nezirus of my father and
I finished 30 days, but if I דווקא davka became an adult
today on day 30 or on day 29 or whatever it was,
so I didn't complete my נזירות, nezirus, then I'm accepting a new
נזירות nezirus now starting today and then 30 days from now he
would bring a קרבן korban because then ממה נפשך mimanishach he'd done
one נזירות. nezirus. Yes, Charlie?
In the case of רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, he would not have
had a conventional way to end the נזירות nezirus because it would
be after the destruction of the Temple.
That
well, רבי חנינא'ס Rabbi Chanina's was it a generation after רבן גמליאל?
Rabban Gamliel?
Right, he was, yeah, he was the generation after
רבן גמליאל.
Rabban
Gamliel.
He lived in Rome.
חנינא, Chanina, what, what which רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel are we talking
about?
Well, it's רבן,
well, רבי חנינא Chanina lived, was a contemporary of רבי יהודה הנשיא.
Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi.
Oh, was he? Okay, I'll try to, I'll try to adjust that.
I don't have the generations straight, but okay.
I was going to ask if this was the same, could it
be the same חנינא Chanina, as רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא?
Rabbi Yossi ben
Rabbi Chanina?
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Rabbi Yossi ben Rabbi Chanina, yeah, so that's,
I don't know either, that's part, I think, that yeah, I don't
know, right.
And so, yes, this has something
to do with all the hokumatization, yeah, right.
I know what you're talking about, חנינא, that's a, you know,
I know there's like two רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yossis floating around and
there's a רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yossi ben Rabbi Chanina floating
around, right, yeah, I don't know, what does Wikipedia say or whoever?
Well, there are a bunch of רבי חנינא'ס. Rabbi Chaninas.
Yeah, a whole bunch. Yeah,
I'm not sure that this, we can assume this was post-Temple.
Is the logic of this argument similar to גר קטן ger katan
that reaches
גיל מצוות gil mitzvot and it just kind of goes away unless
he affirms it?
Something. I mean, there's some idea that it was something, a status
that was imposed and then an ability, it's not exactly the same,
but there's definitely similarities. It's also similar to a question that the
מנחת חינוך Minchat Chinuch has, he has a lot of fun with
this, somebody is, which happens to happen like a good, you know,
15% of the time, kid becomes בר מצוה bar mitzvah in the
middle of the ספירה. sefirah. Right, so does the מצוה mitzvah of
counting the rest of the ספירה, sefirah, is that דאורייתא d'Oraisa or
not? Because does the counting he did pre-בר מצוה bar mitzvah enough
to frame the continued counting as part of a process of counting
50 days, or do we say it was completely meaningless?
And I suppose that's not, I don't remember if
in this גמרא, Gemara, yeah, it would have been relevant. All right,
let's move on. Anyway, that's the end of that סוגיא, sugya, but
it is interesting, the idea that even if, that the question about
when the father can do it if the kid is בר מצוה'ד
bar mitzvahed or the kid is 12, is not necessarily the same
of what stage would end it. בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, which is
a complete independent status, legally independent status, would end it, if it
was imposed by the father, whereas אונס נדרים ones nedarim would not
be, father wouldn't be able to impose it when maybe at אונס
נדרים, ones nedarim, but it would not be strong enough to end
it. Okay, yes.
Does anybody bring in the concept of whether he has the right
to object when he first becomes aware of it as an adult?
Yeah, well, that's the משנה. mishnah. The משנה mishnah says that the
kid can object.
Previous משנה, mishnah, but not here in this case.
Well, you don't even have to object.
He becomes aware or on that, and it's authoritative in the middle,
can he at that point, can he end his נזירות? nezirus?
Yes, that's implicit in the משנה. mishnah. The משנה mishnah says that
if the kid objects or the relatives object, that that ends the
נזירות. nezirus. So this is that being an adult ends it even
without him objecting, but even as a minor he can object and
it ends. That was, the גמרא Gemara didn't explore that part of
the משנה, mishnah, but that was explicit in the משנה. mishnah.
The משנה mishnah said that he or the relatives can object and
it ends it. Now there is a
question תוספות Tosafot raises whether the objection has to be immediate or
not, okay? But so that was not, that's not spelled out in
the משנה. mishnah. What? I have no idea. Let's move on. All
right, next משנה. mishnah. האיש מגלח על נזירות אביו ואין האישה מגלחת
על נזירות אביה. Ha'ish megale'ach al nezirut aviv ve'ein ha'ishah megala'chat al
nezirut aviha. Okay, so this, here's another father-son thing, but not the
son is a minor. Here's a case that we saw earlier where
the father accepts נזירות nezirus and then the father dies and he
left over money, can the son become a נזיר nazir and use
the money that the father left over? So the point in this
משנה mishnah is a son can do it but not a daughter.
So once again, very much father-son.
כיצד, Keitzad, how is this? מי שהיה אביו נזיר והפריש מעות סתומים
על נזירותו ומת ואמר הריני נזיר על מנת שאגלח על מעות אבא.
Mi shehaya aviv nazir vehifrish ma'ot stumim al neziruto umet ve'amar hareni
nazir al menat she'agale'ach al ma'ot aba. Somebody who's a נזיר nazir
and he set aside unspecified funds for his נזירות nezirus and then
he dies and the son said,
I am going to be a
נזיר nazir on the stipulation that I get to use the funds
that the father left. father had set aside. Now remember, normally those
funds would go to an עולה. olah. It’s this magic pile of
unspecified funds which has a certain amount of flexibility what’s going to
happen with it. So here one of the חידוש chiddush is is
that in a normal case it goes to an עולה, olah, but
if the son at that stage accepts נזירות nezirut on the stipulation
to use the funds, he gets to use them for his קרבנות.
korbanot. Okay, הריני נזיר על מנת לגלח על מעות אבא. Hareini nazir
al m'nat legalleiach al me'ot Abba. So אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi
Yosi, הרי אלו יפלו לנדבה, Harei elu yipplu li-nedavah, אמר Amar says
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, if however he did it after the father
died, then the money goes what we normally say goes to those
funds. It goes to an עולה. olah. ואין זה מגלח על נזירות
אביו Ve-ein zeh megalleiach al nezirut aviv and that is not the
case of somebody that gets to use the father's money. איזהו שמגלח
על נזירות אביו? Eizehu she-megalleiach al nezirut aviv? Who's the case of
somebody who gets to use the father's money? Not when he accepts
the נזירות nezirut after the father died, but מי שהיה הוא ואביו
נזירים, Mi she-hayah hu ve-aviv nezirim, he and his father were נזירים
nezirim at the same time, והפריש אביו מעות סתומים לנזירותו Ve-hifrish aviv
me'ot stumim li-neziruto and the father set aside funds for the father's
נזירות. nezirut. ומת U-met and the father died. זהו שמגלח על נזירות
אביו, Zeh she-megalleiach al nezirut aviv, that's the one that gets to
use the father's money. Now that seems a little bit more strange,
because if he and the father were נזירים nezirim at the same
time, then his נזירות nezirut never explicitly, you know, stipulated the ability
to use those funds, and for the first, you know, 29 days
of the נזירות nezirut he was assuming he would have had to
use his own funds, and somehow the the point is was he
and according to this approach, when he and the father are נזירים
nezirim at the same time, they're somehow seen as somehow sharing, doing
it not as two independent parties, but somehow if it's the son
and father doing it together, and maybe this follows the previous idea
that the father imposes the נזירות nezirut on the son, it seems
like it's a family activity. So since, I'm serious, that's the sense
I get, since you're doing it at the same time, it's a
family activity, so if the father dies, the funds get transferred to
the son, but if the son did it after the father died,
then it's not a family activity, then he's just an independent person,
he can't use the father's money. So two different approaches. One is
he דווקא davka gets to use it if he did it after
the father died, because then his נזירות nezirut from the beginning stipulated
that he would use those moneys and those moneys were already a
state that they were somewhat a little indeterminate what was going to
be with that. And the other approach is no, only if he
was doing it participating together with his father as a family activity,
then do the funds get transferred to him. One minute, what?
Wait, so I have two questions. One is, if the father dies,
he is a נזיר, nazir, if the father dies on day 29,
the son has one day or 31?
No, one day, it's the son's, no, one day.
Yeah, okay, right. And why isn't the second model more of a
ירושה yerushah model? Well, it's a ירושה, yerushah, right?
Well, it is, but you don't you don't יורש yoresh money that
money for the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Father sets aside money for
any other קרבן, korban, you don't have a right to use it
for your own קרבנות. korbanot. Exactly, right, exactly. Right, and the גמרא's
Gemara going to get to how much does it follow, but normal
ירושה yerushah wouldn't cover it because this is money that's sanctified for
a קרבן. korban. But it's within that type of concept, it's a
special allowance in the case of נזירות. nezirut. That is correct. Yeah.
Two unrelated people are נזירים. nezirim. Yes. Can one set aside money
for the קרבנות korbanot of both?
Yes,
but it has to be sanctified for that person, and this was
money that was sanctified for the father, no, now it was sanctified
for the father being used by the son. Am I go...
can we go back to the source for a second?
Okay, we'll overlap this one day, what?
Overlap between just one day?
Yeah, exactly. Now there's a whole question about what the גרסא girsa
is, because according to תוספות, Tosafot, right, according to this גרסא, girsa,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says it only works when they were נזירים
nezirim at the same time, but תוספות Tosafot quotes a completely different
גרסא girsa which is the exact reverse. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
says when they're נזירים nezirim at the same time it doesn't work,
it only works when the son accepts נזירות nezirut after the father
died. Let's take a look at our גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא, Mai
ta'ama, what's the reason that a son is able to use the
father's funds for his for the son's קרבנות? korbanot? So אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, הלכה בנזיר היא. Halachah be-nazir hi. Okay, this
getting to sound familiar? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has his stock answer
to all these crazy things, הלכה בנזיר היא. Halachah be-nazir hi. I
don't I can't tell you any source, this is this is just
a הלכה. halachah. Now interestingly, almost always רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan gives
another reason. Either he quotes a פסוק pasuk or he says it's
חינוך, chinuch, but here apparently there's no פסוק, pasuk, no חינוך, chinuch,
nothing else to say, so here ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is silent,
but presumably רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is the only answer that works
here because there's no other way to explain this, that's that's just
the הלכה. halachah. Okay, פשיטא, Pshita, obviously, מאי למימרא, mai le-meimra, דבן
יורש את אביו
בת לא ירשה? de-ven yoresh et aviv bat lo yarshah? So now
the גמרא's Gemara פשיטא pshita is not so much פשיטא pshita on
the whole law, but פשיטא pshita that it's only a son and
not a daughter. Okay, of course, because this gets to this question
about how much is this based on a the normal I construct
of ירושה. yerushah. Okay, especially if you say that it's that the
son does it after the father, you know, accepts נזירות nezirut after
the father died. So the גמרא Gemara says
obviously, all right, all right, obviously. A son inherits his father, not
a daughter. So of course a daughter can't do it. Even if
it was just straight funds she wouldn't be able to get it,
certainly not if they're הקדש hekdesh funds. So לא צריכא דלית ליה
אלא ברתא. Lo tzericha de-leit lei ella barta. No, let's say a
case that he only had a daughter and the daughter would inherit
the rest of his property.
So מהו דתימא יורשין גמרינן לה. mahu de-teima yorshin gamrinan lah. So
maybe we learn it out from the concept of ירושה yerushah and
the same way she inherits the other property. she can use these
funds for her נזירות, nezirus, קא משמע לן kama shma lan הלכה,
halacha, no, that's what the הלכה halacha is. Now again what's also
interesting is that the מאי טעמא הלכה היא mai ta'ama halacha hi
does seem to be not just saying how where do we get
this whole idea that this whole thing works, but it seems to
be answering the question how do we know it only works for
the son and not the daughter? And Rabbi Yochanan says oh that's
a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-moshe mi-sinai. And they must say well
of course anyway we know it. No, no, no, there's a חידוש,
chiddush, even if the daughter would inherit the rest of the property
this is the הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-moshe mi-sinai. So it seems
that part of the point that this is הלכה halacha is not
just to tell you in our question is how do you know
anything, right? The same way by the question about the father doing
a you know making his son a נזיר, nazir, how do you
know any of this? And you have to say הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha le-moshe mi-sinai. But the גמרא Gemara somehow jumps to how do
you know a particular aspect of this, right? Which is posed by
the father making his son a נזיר nazir and by this. How
do you know only sons and not daughters? How do you know
only fathers and not mothers? Oh הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-moshe mi-sinai.
All right, but anyway but again what's funny is that before you
get to the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-moshe mi-sinai to tell you
a nuance in this law you need the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
le-moshe mi-sinai to tell you the whole the whole law to begin
with, right? Anyway fine, but that's what the גמרא Gemara says. According
to Rabbi Yochanan it's הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-moshe mi-sinai that the
son can use the father's money. That הלכה halacha tells you also
only sons and not daughters and you need that חידוש chiddush even
in a case where the daughter the daughter's the only child and
the daughter would generally inherit the funds.
Yeah so the גמרא Gemara wants to broaden and abstract a case
from the
משנה. Mishna. Right, here it wants to to use this to narrow
it down to only focus on some
small well that's because we don't have a general principle, we just
have this sort of arbitrary ruling, right? So we that's part of
the nature of הלכה, halacha, there's a lot of arbitrary parameters and
the only way to explain it is that this whole thing is
just really some arbitrary traditional law. Okay איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu. Now
here's the question פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי יוסי או לא פליגי. pligi
rabanan aleih de-rabbi yosi o lo pligi. When רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
says now we don't know which one רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi was
saying, but let's work with because this will be consistent with the
ברייתא braita we're about to quote. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says it
only works if it's the if the son does it after the
father dies. So it quotes רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi saying it, so
what presumably there's another opinion out there, there's a רבנן rabanan you
know so what do the רבנן rabanan hold? Do the רבנן rabanan
agree with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi or not agree with him? אם
תימא פליגי im teima pligi and if they do and if they
do argue ארישא a-reisha do they argue on the first case when
he says what doesn't work that he says again we'll go with
the version that he says if they were alive at the same
time it doesn't work. Do they disagree with that and say the
same time does work? או אסיפא o a-seifa or do they also
disagree with the end where he says after the death it does
work and maybe the רבנן rabanan say after the death it doesn't?
Right, because there's two points here, what does and what doesn't, right?
You could say the flip, right? רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says alive
at the same time again we'll go with this version I'm saying
after the death works, alive at the same time doesn't. If you
were to disagree you could say the mirror image, right? Or you
could disagree with just one of those הלכות, halachos, say that both
of those times work as opposed to the flip. So that's the
גמרא's Gemara question. So
תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear. כיצד אמרו איש מגלח על
נזירות אביו, keitzad amru ish megalbeach al nezirus aviv, how is it
that a father can use the the son can use the father's
money for his sacrifices? מי שהיה אביו נזיר והפריש אביו מעות לנזירותו
ומת ואמר הריני נזיר על מנת שאגלח על מעות אבא זהו שמגלח
על מעות אביו. mi she-hayah aviv nazir ve-hifrish aviv maos le-neziruso u-mes
ve-amar hareini nazir al menas she-agaleach al maos abba zehu she-megaleach al
maos aviv. Father was a נזיר, nazir, father set aside money for
his נזירות nezirus and he died and he said again this is
after the father died I'm going to use my father's money, זהו
שמגלח על מעות אביו, zehu she-megaleach al maos aviv, that's an acceptable
way to use the father's money. אבל מי שהיה הוא ואביו נזירים
והפריש אביו מעות לנזירותו ומת הרי אלו יפלו לנדבה דברי רבי יוסי.
aval mi she-hayah hu ve-aviv nezirim ve-hifrish aviv maos le-neziruso u-mes harei
elu yiplu le-nedava divrei rabbi yosi. But someone whose father and he
were נזירים nezirim at the same time and then the father set
aside money and the father died הרי אלו יפלו לנדבה harei elu
yiplu le-nedava then that goes to a עולה olah that he cannot
use the money, דברי רבי יוסי. divrei rabbi yosi. So according to
this ברייתא, braita, like this is why we I gave you the
reverse גרסא girsa of what we had printed in our משנה mishna
because this ברייתא braita has רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi explicitly saying that
it's only works after the father died, it does not work if
they were at the same time. So let's assume that's the version
in our משנה mishna as well. Okay so according to רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi this idea works only if the son became a נזיר
nazir after the father died not if it's the same time. רבי
now how but here we get some other voices as well. רבי
אליעזר רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה אמרו זהו שמגלח על מעות אביו. aviv
Nope, in the case where they were נזיר nazir at the same
time he also right that's the most recent latter case here mentioned
in this ברייתא. braita. In the case where they were נזיר nazir
at the same time the son can also use the father's money.
Okay so that's also okay, so you see they say that when
it's at the same time he can use the father's money. Now
does it mean that they disagree in the first case and they
say that after the father died he cannot? Or you know are
they saying the exact mirror image? Or are they saying both cases
the son can use the father's money? Not so clear from this
ברייתא. braita. Anyway what you do see is that you have the
range of positions about whether it's after death which is now what's
רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi case and now presumably that's our גרסא girsa
in the משנה mishna although that's a question, or whether it's only
whether it's okay. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is only after death. The
question is what's the opposing position? Is the opposing position also what
when they're both alive that also works? Or is it no, the...
exact mirror image, only when they were נזירים nezirim at the same
time does it work, after death doesn't work. So we have a
range of possible cases. Now the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to end by
asking some interesting questions about how much, although we
said it's not fully contained
within the laws of ירושה, yerusha, because it would not apply to
a daughter, but how much do the laws of ירושה yerusha to
some degree define the parameters. Okay, and that's going to be the
next series of questions. Let's take a look.
Could they use the money for their own sacrifice? How could the
son or even just pay for the... for the sacrifice? Or the
daughter, wouldn't that be allowed?
From their own money? No,
no, no, no, first of all they can use their money from
their own bank account. But second of all, second of all, I
don't know, what are you talking about? The son's been an investment
banker for the last 30 years and then his father died. I
don't understand the question number one. But number two is, we're not
talking about minors. Number two is that any money you inherit that's
not sanctified, you can use for whatever you want. We're talking about
the sanctified monies can only be... that's the issue. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay.
בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, רבא Rava asks. יש לו שני בנים נזירים.
Yesh lo sheni banim nezirim. He had two sons who were נזירים.
nezirim. Again, whether this is the version that they were alive at
the same
time and that they were נזירים nezirim at the same time or
whether it's the version that they became נזיר nazir after the father
died. Doesn't matter. Okay. However you work it out, you have two...
a guy left two sons that are now נזירים. nezirim. They want
to use the father's funds. Okay, and it would be in a
scenario where if it was one son, he could use the father's...
sons... sanctified funds. מהו? Mahu? What's the... what's the הלכה halakha about
who gets to use the funds? הלכתא גמרינן לה. Hilkheta gamrinan lah.
כל דקדים גלח, גלח. Kol dekadim galach, galach. Do we say this
is not based on ירושה yerusha at all, it's just an arbitrary
הלכה halakha within נזירות nezirut and may therefore maybe, you know, first
come first serve? Whoever goes ahead and brings his קרבנות korbanot first
gets to use that money,
first one to, you know, take... you know, take the money and
use it gets the right to use it? או דילמא, O dilma,
or do we say ירושה גמרינן לה. Yerusha gamrinan lah. No, even
if there's a הלכה halakha part to this that it's... you know,
that it... nevertheless it's based on some of the laws of ירושה.
yerusha. ופלגא הוי, Upalga havei, and each son gets to use half
the funds. Okay, so that's a good question, right? One also wonders
what would happen if one son, let's say it was a case
when they did it after the father died. So the father died,
one son became a נזיר nazir and he was... it was his
turn to bring the קרבנות, korbanot, and the other son said like,
wait, wait, wait, I'm planning on being a נזיר nazir in a
month from now, not now, but I'm planning on it. You only
get to use half, right? If you say they split it, right,
at what stage do they both have to be נזירים? nezirim? Let's
say the other son became a נזיר nazir 20 days into the
first son's נזירות. nezirut. Let's say the other son became a נזיר
nazir after the son's 30 days were up but before he brought
the קרבן. korban. Like at what stage does the second son get
a right to say, I'm entitled to half to use funds? That
the גמרא Gemara doesn't explore. No, the גמרא Gemara explores an easier
case, they're both נזירים nezirim at the same time. I'm just building
on the גמרא'ס Gemara's case, okay? So the first question is if
both נזירים nezirim at the same time, do we fundamentally say the
funds go all to one son who wants to use it, first
come first serve? Or do we say that even though this doesn't
apply to daughters, it only applies to sons, but within the category
of sons, we are going to be guided by laws of ירושה
yerusha and we're going to say it gets split between the two
sons. Okay, but my only question is what qualifies the both sons
as being entitled within this world of נזירות, nezirut, you know, do
they both have to be נזירים nezirim at the same time? Whatever.
That's... to be explored even further. Now we're going to have another
variation of this question. Okay. בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, רבא Rava asks
the following question. בכור ופשוט, Bechor upashut, let's say one of them
is a firstborn son and the other is a normal son. So
the first one gets two... you know, two portions. מאי? Mai? הלכתא
גמרינן לה, Hilkheta gamrinan lah, הלכך לאו בדילוגי, hilkach lav bidilugei, לפום
מאי דשקיל. lefom mai deshakeil. So therefore, do we say this is
הלכה halakha and therefore you don't get to literally shave, but you
don't get to take the monies, you know, for your קרבנות korbanot
according to your proportion in the ירושה. yerusha. Meaning maybe we'll say
that fine, the sons split it, but maybe they don't split it
exactly according to ירושה yerusha laws, even the בכור bechor gets only
an equal portion, maybe we say that? או דילמא, O dilma, or
do we say ירושה היא. Yerusha hi. No, no, no, we're going
to follow ירושה yerusha laws consistently here. וכי היכי דשקיל פי שנים,
Uki heichi deshakeil pi shenayim, הכא נמי מגלח. hacha nami megale'ach. The
same way he would get two portions in terms of other funds,
he gets two portions out of the funds towards his קרבנות. korbanot.
So how much are we going to even... even to the degree
of the idea of בכור bechor follow those laws? ואם תמצי לומר
ירושה היא, Ve'im timtzi lomar yerusha hi, if we say that it
is going to follow the laws of ירושה. yerusha. ולפום דשקיל מגלח,
Ulefom deshakeil megale'ach, and he uses the money for his קרבנות korbanot
according to his normal portion of the ירושה. yerusha. ובחולין הוא דאית
ליה פי שנים, Ubechulin hu de'it lei pi shenayim, אבל בהקדש לא.
aval behekedesh lo.
Do we say it's only for חולין chulin purposes and not for
הקדש? hekdesh? או דילמא, O dilma, כיון דקני ליה לגילוח לא שנא.
keivan dekani lei legilu'ach lo shena.
Or since it's for the purpose of shaving and his קרבנות, korbanot,
it doesn't matter. Now what does this mean, for חולין chulin or
for הקדש? hekdesh? All of this is for הקדש. hekdesh. All of
this is to bring
his
קרבנות. korbanot. What difference does it make? Either way, it's the same
point. Who cares whether he uses this word or that word? It's
the exact same הלכה. halacha. So the רא"ש Rosh does not like
that answer. If you take a look at the רא"ש, Rosh, he
says the following. He
says
ואם תמצא לומר, ve'im timtzo lomar, it is basically, we see the
תוספות Tosafot that says אביו like in the first wide-line תוספות. Tosafot.
Go across from there and go back down two lines in the
רא"ש Rosh where it says ואם תמצא לומר ve'im timtzo lomar at
the beginning of a line.
Exactly. ואם תמצא לומר, ve'im timtzo lomar, לפום מאי דשקיל מגלח. lefu
mai deshakil megaleach. בחולין הוא דאיתא פי שנים, bechullin hu de'isa pi
shenayim, כגון שאמר אביו אלו לנזירותי, kegon she'amar aviv elu leneziruti, ואמר
לקרבנות נזירותי. ve'amar lekorbanot neziruti.
Oh no, I'm sorry, it's not that the son said that it's
for the נזירות nezirut or the קרבנות, korbanot, it's whether the father
said it. אבל בהקדש לא, aval behekdesh lo, אם אמר לקרבנות נזירותי.
im amar lekorbanot neziruti. But maybe it wouldn't apply בהקדש behekdesh if
the father explicitly said קרבנות. korbanot. והוא הדין דמצי למיבעי גם בפשוט,
vihu din dematzi lemibaye gam befashut,
we don't have to ask this question only by the בכור, bechor,
we could have just had it in a general question. אי גמירי
הלכה במותי דהקדש, i gemiri halacha bemosei dehekdesh, does it apply when
the father explicitly labeled the money as הקדש? hekdesh? ופירוש זר הוא,
uferush zar hu, that's a bizarre explanation. And because besides that the
גמרא Gemara seems to only be asking it in the context of
a בכור, bechor, what difference does it make if the father said
נזירות nezirut or קרבנות נזירות? korbanot nezirut? It means the same thing,
he's מקדיש maktish the funds. ונראה לפרש, venire lefaresh, דסיומא דמילתא הוא,
desiyuma demilsa hu, that it's ending the discussion of the בכור. bechor.
ואם תמצא לומר, ve'im timtzo lomar, ירושה הוא, yerusha hu, לפום מאי
דשקיל מגלח. lefu mai deshakil megaleach. Okay,
so if we say that it follows the laws of ירושה yerusha
and it follows the proportion you normally get. דבי פשוטין כל חד
מגלח לפום מאי דשקיל. debei peshutin kol chad megaleach lefu mai deshakil.
ואמרינן כל הקודם מגלח. ve'ominan kol hakedem megaleach.
So first we say so fine, by normal sons each one gets
an equal portion if it's two sons. אחרי
הכי אפשר, achrei hachi efshar, בכור פשוט לא מגלח, bechor pashut lo
megaleach, או לפום מאי דשקיל בשאר נכסים. o lefu mai deshakil bishear
nechasim. Or do we say that fine, that's by two sons. But
if it was a בכור bechor and a פשוט, pashut, then it
would not get two portions. Why?
דבכורין הוא דשקיל פי שנים. debechorin hu deshakil pi shenayim. When does
the בכור bechor get
a double portion? דקרינן ביה בכל אשר ימצא לו, dekarinan bei bechol
asher yimatze lo,
because by the בכור bechor it says he gets double with the
funds, the money that is found, that is like available. Okay, and
that idea that it's available is less relevant by הקדש. hekdesh. הקדש
hekdesh isn't really available funds, they're really pre-designated for הקדש. hekdesh. או
דילמא לא שנא, o dilma lo shana, maybe it doesn't matter. So
what he's saying is this idea of חולין chullin and הקדש hekdesh
is not a new question. It's sharpening the point about the בכור.
bechor. Even if we normally say it follows ירושה yerusha rules in
terms of dividing the funds, maybe not by בכור. bechor. Why should
בכור bechor be different? That's part of ירושה yerusha rules. No, בכור
bechor maybe is an idea that's fundamentally really only relevant to חולין.
chullin. Because בכור bechor has this idea בכל אשר ימצא לו, bechol
asher yimatze lo, the funds have to be, the money have to
be available. But by הקדש, hekdesh, even if there's a rule here
that הקדש hekdesh funds get divided, נזירות nezirut הקדש hekdesh funds get
divided, that would not be relevant for בכור. bechor. בכור bechor fundamentally
is not relevant to the world of הקדש hekdesh because it doesn't
satisfy בכל אשר ימצא לו. bechol asher yimatze lo. So according to
the רא"ש Rosh this question of חולין chullin and הקדש hekdesh is
a way of clarifying why בכור bechor might be different. Okay, let's
now read the last question. אביו נזיר עולם, aviv nazir olam, now.
אביו נזיר עולם והוא נזיר
סתם, aviv nazir olam vehu nazir stam,
let's say he and his father are different types of נזירים. nezirim.
His father is a נזיר עולם nazir olam and he's a נזיר
סתם. nazir stam. Now you'll tell me if his father is a
נזיר עולם, nazir olam, why does he have funds for קרבנות? korbanot?
The father's נזירות nezirut is never going to end. But because you'll
remember that a נזיר עולם nazir olam gets to take a haircut
once every thirty days or once every year, but only when he
brings the right, the קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so all right. So let's
say they're different types of נזירים, nezirim, can you reassign the funds
from type A to type B? אביו נזיר סתם והוא נזיר עולם,
מאי? aviv nazir stam vehu nazir olam, mai? What do we say?
כי גמינן הלכתא בסתם נזירות, ki geminan hilchasa bistam nezirut, does it
apply just for normal נזירות? nezirut? או דילמא לא שנא, o dilma
lo shana, does it not matter? Now you could also say as
תוספות Tosafot says, you could also ask the question if they're both
נזיר עולם. nazir olam. Maybe even if they're the same type, maybe
this הלכה halacha only applies to normal נזירות nezirut and not to
סתם stam and not to נזיר עולם. nazir olam. But even if
it applies to נזיר עולם, nazir olam, maybe it only applies when
the father and the son are the same, not when they're different.
ואם תמצא לומר, ve'im timtzo lomar, או דילמא לא שנא. o dilma
lo shana. ואם תמצא לומר הכא האי והאי נזירות טהרה. ve'im timtzo
lomar hacha adei adei nezirut tahara. And if
you say no, it doesn't matter if the father's a נזיר עולם
nazir olam and the son is a נזיר, nazir, is a regular
נזיר, nazir, they're both טהרה tahara נזירותס, neziruses, so you can apply
the funds. But בעי רב אשי: Bayei Rav Ashi: אביו נזיר טמא
והוא נזיר טהור. aviu nazir tamei ve-hu nazir tahor. Let's say the
money was applied for different types of קרבנות, korbanot, not just different
נזירות. nezirus. Different נזירות, nezirus, whether נזיר עולם, nazir olam, נזיר סתם,
nazir stam, it's the same animal, same קרבנות. korbanot. But let's say
the father set aside the money because the father had become טמא
tamei and then he would have brought different קרבנות, korbanot, birds instead
of sheep and so on, right? And for the purpose of טומאה,
tumah, not for the purpose of ending the נזירות. nezirus. And then
the father died. Can the son use it for נזירות טהרה? nezirus
tahara? Okay? Or אביו נזיר טהור והוא נזיר טמא מאי? aviu nazir
tahor ve-hu nazir tamei mai? What about the reverse? תיקו. teiku. So
we're going to leave that with a standing question. And הדרן עלך
מי שאמר. Hadran Alach Mi She'amar. So we successfully actually finished our
full דף. daf.